<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<screen>-= Info about application &apos;Directory&apos; =-

[Synopsis]
Provide directory of voicemail extensions

[Description]
  Directory(vm-context[,dial-context[,options]]): This application will present
the calling channel with a directory of extensions from which they can search
by name. The list of names and corresponding extensions is retrieved from the
voicemail configuration file, voicemail.conf.
  This application will immediately exit if one of the following DTMF digits are
received and the extension to jump to exists:
    0 - Jump to the &apos;o&apos; extension, if it exists.
    * - Jump to the &apos;a&apos; extension, if it exists.

  Parameters:
    vm-context   - This is the context within voicemail.conf to use for the
                   Directory.
    dial-context - This is the dialplan context to use when looking for an
                   extension that the user has selected, or when jumping to the
                   &apos;o&apos; or &apos;a&apos; extension.

  Options:
    e           In addition to the name, also read the extension number to the
              caller before presenting dialing options.
    f[(&lt;n&gt;)]    Allow the caller to enter the first name of a user in the
              directory instead of using the last name.  If specified, the
              optional number argument will be used for the number of
              characters the user should enter.
    l[(&lt;n&gt;)]    Allow the caller to enter the last name of a user in the
              directory.  This is the default.  If specified, the
              optional number argument will be used for the number of
              characters the user should enter.
    b[(&lt;n&gt;)]    Allow the caller to enter either the first or the last name
              of a user in the directory.  If specified, the optional number
              argument will be used for the number of characters the user
              should enter.
    m           Instead of reading each name sequentially and asking for
              confirmation, create a menu of up to 8 names.
    p(&lt;n&gt;)      Pause for n milliseconds after the digits are typed.  This is
              helpful for people with cellphones, who are not holding the
              receiver to their ear while entering DTMF.

    Only one of the f, l, or b options may be specified.  If more than one is
    specified, then Directory will act as if &apos;b&apos; was specified.  The number
    of characters for the user to type defaults to 3.<screen>
