<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="kapitel-howto" lang="de" revision="$Revision: 1102 $">
  <!--% Copyright (c) 2006 - 2008 by Stefan Wintermeyer <sw@amooma.de>
% Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
% under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
% or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
% with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover
% Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
% Free Documentation License".
% Asterisk training and consulting is offered at http://www.amooma.de-->

  <title>A "How-to" for this book</title>

  <para>First, thank you for buying this book. It's only through the interest
  of readers like you that a project like this is possible.</para>

  <para>We wrote this book because Asterisk doesn't come with an instruction
  manual. Many of the resources recommended by members of the Asterisk
  community are in the form of wikis and websites which are inconsistently
  updated and often contain information that is incorrect. We wanted this book
  to serve as that missing manual to Asterisk. In other words, we wanted to
  create the kind of book we were looking for: a readable text that can be
  read in chapter order or used as a handbook.</para>

  <section id="was-ist-asterisk">
    <title>What is Asterisk?</title>

    <para>Asterisk is a telephone system, but different. It's not hardware,
    it's software that can be downloaded via the Internet. The only thing you
    need to get started is an ordinary PC, the Asterisk software, this book
    and interest.</para>

    <para>Asterisk works with a variety of technologies, including analog
    telephone, ISDN telephone and VoIP. With an Asterisk system, an employee
    can work at home with an IP phone and make calls in the office system as
    though she were in the office. The possibilities are limitless, both to
    extend the functionality of your system and to save money. Telephony
    remains sophisticated, however, and a move to Asterisk is not without its
    challenges. You need to become comfortable and familiar with both the
    technology and with Asterisk itself.</para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Asterisk</primary>

      <secondary>Differences from a traditional PBX</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Let's explore the difference between Asterisk and a conventional
    telephone system by way of an analogy from childhood.</para>

    <para>Most of us grew up with toys of two basic types. With the first
    type, everything came "ready to go", as it would in the case of model cars
    or teddy bears. The second type offered some room for variation and
    creativity, as in the case of Lego blocks. With the "ready to go" toys,
    the fun was right there when you opened the package, but you were limited
    to play as conceived by the toy company. With the blocks, you didn't get a
    finished toy. To get one, you had to come up with a design and then build
    it, but you could build anything you wanted, within the limitations of the
    pieces available.</para>

    <para>That, in a nutshell, is exactly how it is with Asterisk. It is
    delivered in pieces. Think of a design, and suddenly anything is possible.
    Best of all, you can improve the resulting "toy" any time with new
    pieces.</para>

    <para>Both types have their pros and cons.</para>

    <para><emphasis>The main advantages of a conventional telephone system
    are:</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Unpack and you're done! You can start making calls almost
        immediately.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Limited instructions are required.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis>The main disadvantages of a conventional telephone system
    are:</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Expansion is usually very expensive, and not all functions are
        supported or even available.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It's a black box. You have no way to find out what's happening
        inside, which can be vital when troubleshooting.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis>The main advantages of a software-based Asterisk
    system:</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can build new solutions to problems any time. All you need
        is an appropriate design.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can combine components to create new systems and
        solutions.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis>The main disadvantages of Asterisk:</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You start with: a bunch of components. Building them into a
        system requires some patience.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You need some skill. Success doesn't come quickly.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="womit-anfangen">
    <title>Who Should Read this Book?</title>

    <para>Not everybody has to start at square one, nor does every interested
    person want to become an Asterisk professional. This book is intended for
    both and will be a valuable reference for beginners, novices and experts
    alike.</para>

    <section id="anfaenger-howto">
      <title>The Beginner</title>

      <para>Absolute beginners should read the book in chapter order, since
      the chapters build on each other. You can start with <xref
      linkend="chapter-installation" /> and read until the end. At a minimum,
      read through <xref linkend="chapter-installation" /> and <xref
      linkend="chapter-programming" /> and you'll be able to put together more
      complex telephone systems. If you have programming experience, you might
      try getting started with <xref linkend="programmer-howto" />.</para>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>FAQ</primary>

        <secondary>Beginner's FAQ</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Beginners often have questions about what equipment is best to buy
      and which service to order, so we've provided this brief FAQ for those
      who need some guidance.</para>

      <qandaset>
        <qandadiv>
          <qandaentry>
            <question>
              <para>How do I choose a VoIP provider? What do I need to watch
              out for?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>When starting out, choose a SIP provider that offers free
              accounts so that you can gather some experience. Which provider
              you choose for the long term can depend on many factors. Here
              are but a few things to consider:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Does the provider offer only SIP or also IAX? Do you
                  need IAX?</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>How good is the support? For VoIP, good support can be
                  critical.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>How is the pricing? This is not always obvious.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

          <qandaentry>
            <question>
              <para>Which digital interface card should I use?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>Get comfortable using only SIP trunks and extensions to
              start. Once you understand the dialplan and contexts, you can
              proceed to the <link linkend="kapitel-isdn">ISDN-Kapitel</link>,
              where there are tips for choosing the right digital card for
              your application.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

          <qandaentry>
            <question>
              <para>Which phones are standard and what do they cost?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>There aren't really "standard" phones. You have several
              options:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>A SIP telephone (this is the simplest option)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>An analog telephone using an ATA (analog telephone
                  adapter) connected to the network</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>An analog telephone using an FXS port on an analog
                  interface card</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>A digital telephone (such as a Nortel Meridian phone)
                  using a suitable digital telephone adapter connected to the
                  network</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>An ISDN phone using a port on a T1 card. These phones
                  are sold almost exclusively in Europe where ISDN termination
                  is much more common. Before the arrival of VoIP, they were
                  the most feature-filled devices; nowadays they are
                  functionally indistinguishable from VoIP phones and can cost
                  three times as much. If you have the option, it's best to go
                  with a SIP telephone.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Exotic constructs. You can, for example, connect a
                  channel bank to a T1 interface card and attach analog phones
                  to the channel bank. Such constructions are generally useful
                  in retrofit applications. If you're starting from scratch,
                  keep it simple.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>

              <para>As for pricing, this changes constantly. There are
              countless suppliers. Inquire frequently and compare. Quality
              VoIP hardware is becoming more and more affordable.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>
        </qandadiv>
      </qandaset>
    </section>

    <section id="medium-howto">
      <title>The Journeyman</title>

      <para>It would be impossible to guess what an intermediate Asterisk user
      knows and doesn't know. Even if you have good command of a subject there
      are always aspects to it that might be new. If you have some practical
      experience, you could skip <xref linkend="chapter-installation" /> or
      just skim through it. Personally, though, we can only recommend that you
      read it anyway. It almost always pays off.</para>

      <para>Leaf through the additional chapters afterwards. In writing the
      book we focused on practical examples. Just reading the example
      configurations can give you some new ideas.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="profi-howto">
      <title>The Expert</title>

      <para>You can skip <xref linkend="chapter-installation" /> and just go
      on a discovery tour of the book. There are numerous practical examples
      you can employ immediately in your own practice; the examples may even
      give you a few new ideas.</para>

      <para>Beyond that, we hope this book will be a valuable reference. All
      the important application and function parameters are included and
      explained, usually with working examples. We placed particular emphasis
      on comparisons between the different Asterisk versions (1.2 to
      1.6).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="updates-und-versionen-des-buches">
    <title>Updates and versions of the book</title>

    <para>This book is being developed as a typical open source project would
    be. What you are holding in your hands is a printed version of the stable
    branch. Updates and errata can be found at <ulink
    url="http://das-asterisk-buch.de"><citetitle>http://www.the-asterisk-book.com</citetitle></ulink>.</para>

    <para>You'll find the current SVN version there. That'll be the next
    edition, but for now it is on the bleeding edge. The procedures contained
    there may not have been tested and may not even be recommended. Therefore,
    a warning: use that material only if you know what you're doing.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="feedback">
    <title>Reader Contributions and Feedback</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>FAQ</primary>

        <secondary>FAQ for volunteers</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <para>We intended this book to be a living text. This is why it was
    released under the GNU Free Documentation License (see <xref
    linkend="gnu-fdl" />). This is why you can find the most current version
    of the book at <ulink
    url="http://das-asterisk-buch.de"><citetitle>http://www.the-asterisk-book.com</citetitle></ulink>.</para>

    <para>If you have suggestions for improvements, include it in an e-mail to
    <email>stefan.wintermeyer@amooma.de</email>. If you have more
    comprehensive improvements to contribute, attach them in ASCII text format
    or directly in <ulink
    url="http://www.docbook.org"><citetitle>DocBook</citetitle></ulink> format
    to your e-mail.</para>

    <para>Thanks in advance for your interest in this project!</para>

    <para>There are numerous ways you can help support the project, from
    providing a positive review for the book on Amazon.com, all the way to
    contributing a chapter that addresses a specific problem.</para>

    <para>This book will never be perfect and also never really "finished".
    The subject is too complex and changes too rapidly. Remember that you can
    always find the most current (and most bleeding-edge) version of the book
    at <ulink
    url="http://das-asterisk-buch.de"><citetitle>http://www.the-asterisk-book.com</citetitle></ulink>.
    Accordingly, this FAQ is intended for the web version of the book. If you
    find an error in the book, please check the website first to see if the
    error has already been fixed.</para>

    <qandaset>
      <qandadiv>
        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>I tried something from the book, but it didn't work as
            described. Should I report this?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>Yes, absolutely! When reporting, provide the URL and any
            relevant error messages.</para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>

        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>How can I report an error?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>The easiest way is with an e-mail to the author, Stefan
            Wintermeyer: <email>stefan.wintermeyer@amooma.de.</email></para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>
      </qandadiv>

      <qandadiv>
        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>In what format is the book written?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>The source for the book is written in DocBook format. You
            can learn more about DocBook at <ulink
            url="http://www.docbook.org">http://www.docbook.org</ulink>.</para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>

        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>Why isn't there a wiki, where anybody can make
            changes?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>First: Because the book is printed, a print deadline has to
            be set. A constantly changing text makes it impossible for the
            editors to keep up and keep the resulting printed material
            consistent. Second: There are already numerous Asterisk wikis on
            the Internet; their chief advantage (quick and easy changes) also
            leads to their chief disadvantage: mountains of painfully outdated
            and outright incorrect information. Using DocBook and managing
            changes means we have a more structured, more readable text that
            is as accurate as human beings can make it.</para>

            <para>If the entire text were in a wiki, it would make export for
            printing very difficult.</para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>

        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>What editor do I need to write in DocBook format?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>That's almost a "religious" question. Some people like
            emacs, others like vi. The author and contributors use XMLmind XML
            Editor most of the time. You can obtain it from <ulink
            url="http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/"><citetitle>http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/</citetitle></ulink>.</para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>

        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>Can I obtain the original DocBook files?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>Yes. If you have extensive changes to make, you are welcome
            to work on the original files. Write an e-mail to the author,
            Stefan Wintermeyer:
            <email>stefan.wintermeyer@amooma.de</email>.</para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>

        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>You didn't cover XYZ! Unbelievable. It's so important! What
            were you thinking?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>Contact the author at
            <email>stefan.wintermeyer@amooma.de</email> and briefly describe
            the subject.</para>

            <para>If you're willing to write a chapter and make it available
            under the GNU FDL, let Stefan know. He'll send you a sample
            DocBook chapter.</para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>

        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>How is the website generated?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>A script pulls the DocBook sources from the SVN and uses
            them to generate the HTML pages.</para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>
      </qandadiv>
    </qandaset>
  </section>

  <section id="problem">
    <title>Further Resources</title>

    <para>You have a problem and weren't able to find the answer in this book?
    Here are your options:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.voip-info.org"><citetitle>http://www.voip-info.org</citetitle></ulink></para>

        <para>This site is dedicated to VoIP in general and to Asterisk and it
        offers solutions to most problems. Unfortunately, many of the articles
        contain errors. If you find one, fix it! The next visitor will be
        grateful.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>IRC Channel<indexterm>
            <primary>IRC Channel</primary>
          </indexterm></para>

        <para>There is an Asterisk IRC channel, <code>#asterisk</code> at
        <ulink
        url="http://freenode.net/"><citetitle>irc.freenode.net</citetitle></ulink>.
        It's sometimes possible to get a quick answer to your question there,
        though be warned: some of the channel participants have a low
        tolerance for laziness. You improve your chances of success by
        thinking your question through carefully. Generally, the motto
        "explaining your problem is half the solution" applies.</para>

        <para>If you are new to IRC, you can learn more about it at <ulink
        url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Relay_Chat"><citetitle>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Relay_Chat</citetitle></ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mailing lists<indexterm>
            <primary>Mailing lists</primary>
          </indexterm></para>

        <para>The Digium mailing lists are not for everybody. The list has
        very high volume and a new list user can be quickly overwhelmed.
        Still, it has a few significant advantages: it's read by Digium staff
        and they often answer questions. You can also get more detailed
        answers than is typical for IRC. You can find out how to subscribe to
        the mailing lists at <ulink
        url="http://www.asterisk.org/support/"><citetitle>http://www.asterisk.org/support/</citetitle></ulink>
        and <ulink
        url="http://lists.digium.com/"><citetitle>http://lists.digium.com/</citetitle></ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>E-Mail Stefan Wintermeyer
        (<email>stefan.wintermeyer@amooma.de)</email></para>

        <para>If all else fails, you can always try contacting the author.
        Just be warned that he gets a lot of mail and may not get to your
        question for several days.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
