<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="media-gateways" lang="de" revision="$Revision: 1899 $">
  <!--% Copyright (c) 2009 - Stefan Wintermeyer <sw@amooma.de>
% Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
% under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
% or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
% with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover
% Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
% Free Documentation License".
% Asterisk training and consulting is offered at http://www.amooma.de-->

  <title>Media Gateways</title>

  <section id="media-gateways-einleitung">
    <title>Basics</title>

    <para>Just as you might use an ATA in place of an analog interface card
    for regular phones, you could use a "media gateway" for ISDN connections.
    This gateway converts an ISDN connection into one or more SIP accounts and
    vice-versa. These are usually "black box" solutions, which are configured
    via a web GUI or over SSH.</para>

    <para>Purely analog media gateways are simply ATAs (Analog Telephone
    Adapters), see <xref linkend="ata" />.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="media-gateways-vorteile">
    <title>Advantages</title>

    <para>One major advantage is that a media gateway is often easier to
    configure than an interface card. You don't have to open up the server and
    install the card, either. Configuring Asterisk is simpler, because you
    only have to configure SIP. Finally, you don't have to run telephone lines
    of any kind to the server; you install the gateway device in the wire
    room, connect it to the network patch panel, and put the server anywhere
    on the network that is practical.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="media-gateways-nachteile">
    <title>Disadvantages</title>

    <para>Media gateways are generally sold on price and not on the quality of
    installed components, so manufacturers are tempted to use lower quality
    interface cards, which can be problematic (see <xref
    linkend="which-isdn-card" />). Asterisk works best when using the ISDN
    clock; the clock signal is very stable, and a stable clock signal is
    vital, especially for conferencing. A media gateway does not pass this
    signal over Ethernet; the Asterisk server must rely on the system clock,
    which will vary in stability. Updating a media gateway is also more
    difficult, if it's possible at all.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="media-gateways-fazit">
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>Whether one should choose an interface card or a media gateway is a
    regular topic of discussion in the Asterisk community. Both sides make
    good arguments, and you can run a successful system with either. What is
    best for you depends on the circumstances. If you need stable clock (you
    are conferencing or you have existing ISDN cards in your system), you'll
    need an ISDN card. If you have physical access problems, or you need to
    maximize the simplicity of the system, go with a media gateway.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
