<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<screen>-= Info about application &apos;Dial&apos; =-

[Synopsis]
Place a call and connect to the current channel

[Description]
  Dial(Technology/resource[&amp;Tech2/resource2...][,timeout][,options][,URL]):
This application will place calls to one or more specified channels. As soon
as one of the requested channels answers, the originating channel will be
answered, if it has not already been answered. These two channels will then
be active in a bridged call. All other channels that were requested will then
be hung up.
  Unless there is a timeout specified, the Dial application will wait
indefinitely until one of the called channels answers, the user hangs up, or
if all of the called channels are busy or unavailable. Dialplan executing will
continue if no requested channels can be called, or if the timeout expires.

  This application sets the following channel variables upon completion:
    DIALEDTIME   - This is the time from dialing a channel until when it
                   is disconnected.
    ANSWEREDTIME - This is the amount of time for actual call.
    DIALSTATUS   - This is the status of the call:
                   CHANUNAVAIL | CONGESTION | NOANSWER | BUSY | ANSWER | CANCEL
                   DONTCALL | TORTURE | INVALIDARGS
  For the Privacy and Screening Modes, the DIALSTATUS variable will be set to
DONTCALL if the called party chooses to send the calling party to the &apos;Go Away&apos;
script. The DIALSTATUS variable will be set to TORTURE if the called party
wants to send the caller to the &apos;torture&apos; script.
  This application will report normal termination if the originating channel
hangs up, or if the call is bridged and either of the parties in the bridge
ends the call.
  The optional URL will be sent to the called party if the channel supports it.
  If the OUTBOUND_GROUP variable is set, all peer channels created by this
application will be put into that group (as in Set(GROUP()=...).
  If the OUTBOUND_GROUP_ONCE variable is set, all peer channels created by this
application will be put into that group (as in Set(GROUP()=...). Unlike OUTBOUND_GROUP,
however, the variable will be unset after use.

  Options:
    A(x) - Play an announcement to the called party, using &apos;x&apos; as the file.
    C    - Reset the CDR for this call.
    c    - If DIAL cancels this call, always set the flag to tell the channel
           driver that the call is answered elsewhere.
    d    - Allow the calling user to dial a 1 digit extension while waiting for
           a call to be answered. Exit to that extension if it exists in the
           current context, or the context defined in the EXITCONTEXT variable,
           if it exists.
    D([called][:calling]) - Send the specified DTMF strings *after* the called
           party has answered, but before the call gets bridged. The &apos;called&apos;
           DTMF string is sent to the called party, and the &apos;calling&apos; DTMF
           string is sent to the calling party. Both parameters can be used
           alone.
    e    - execute the &apos;h&apos; extension for peer after the call ends
    f    - Force the callerid of the *calling* channel to be set as the
           extension associated with the channel using a dialplan &apos;hint&apos;.
           For example, some PSTNs do not allow CallerID to be set to anything
           other than the number assigned to the caller.
    F(context^exten^pri) - When the caller hangs up, transfer the called party
           to the specified context and extension and continue execution.
    g    - Proceed with dialplan execution at the current extension if the
           destination channel hangs up.
    G(context^exten^pri) - If the call is answered, transfer the calling party to
           the specified priority and the called party to the specified priority+1.
           Optionally, an extension, or extension and context may be specified.
           Otherwise, the current extension is used. You cannot use any additional
           action post answer options in conjunction with this option.
    h    - Allow the called party to hang up by sending the &apos;*&apos; DTMF digit.
    H    - Allow the calling party to hang up by hitting the &apos;*&apos; DTMF digit.
    i    - Asterisk will ignore any forwarding requests it may receive on this
           dial attempt.
    k    - Allow the called party to enable parking of the call by sending
           the DTMF sequence defined for call parking in features.conf.
    K    - Allow the calling party to enable parking of the call by sending
           the DTMF sequence defined for call parking in features.conf.
    L(x[:y][:z]) - Limit the call to &apos;x&apos; ms. Play a warning when &apos;y&apos; ms are
           left. Repeat the warning every &apos;z&apos; ms. The following special
           variables can be used with this option:
           * LIMIT_PLAYAUDIO_CALLER   yes|no (default yes)
                                      Play sounds to the caller.
           * LIMIT_PLAYAUDIO_CALLEE   yes|no
                                      Play sounds to the callee.
           * LIMIT_TIMEOUT_FILE       File to play when time is up.
           * LIMIT_CONNECT_FILE       File to play when call begins.
           * LIMIT_WARNING_FILE       File to play as warning if &apos;y&apos; is defined.
                                      The default is to say the time remaining.
    m([class]) - Provide hold music to the calling party until a requested
           channel answers. A specific MusicOnHold class can be
           specified.
    M(x[^arg]) - Execute the Macro for the *called* channel before connecting
           to the calling channel. Arguments can be specified to the Macro
           using &apos;^&apos; as a delimiter. The Macro can set the variable
           MACRO_RESULT to specify the following actions after the Macro is
           finished executing.
           * ABORT        Hangup both legs of the call.
           * CONGESTION   Behave as if line congestion was encountered.
           * BUSY         Behave as if a busy signal was encountered.
           * CONTINUE     Hangup the called party and allow the calling party
                          to continue dialplan execution at the next priority.
           * GOTO:&lt;context&gt;^&lt;exten&gt;^&lt;priority&gt; - Transfer the call to the
                          specified priority. Optionally, an extension, or
                          extension and priority can be specified.
           You cannot use any additional action post answer options in conjunction
           with this option. Also, pbx services are not run on the peer (called) channel,
           so you will not be able to set timeouts via the TIMEOUT() function in this macro.
    n    - This option is a modifier for the screen/privacy mode. It specifies
           that no introductions are to be saved in the priv-callerintros
           directory.
    N    - This option is a modifier for the screen/privacy mode. It specifies
           that if callerID is present, do not screen the call.
    o    - Specify that the CallerID that was present on the *calling* channel
           be set as the CallerID on the *called* channel. This was the
           behavior of Asterisk 1.0 and earlier.
    O([x]) - &quot;Operator Services&quot; mode (DAHDI channel to DAHDI channel
             only, if specified on non-DAHDI interface, it will be ignored).
             When the destination answers (presumably an operator services
             station), the originator no longer has control of their line.
             They may hang up, but the switch will not release their line
             until the destination party hangs up (the operator). Specified
             without an arg, or with 1 as an arg, the originator hanging up
             will cause the phone to ring back immediately. With a 2 specified,
             when the &quot;operator&quot; flashes the trunk, it will ring their phone
             back.
    p    - This option enables screening mode. This is basically Privacy mode
           without memory.
    P([x]) - Enable privacy mode. Use &apos;x&apos; as the family/key in the database if
           it is provided. The current extension is used if a database
           family/key is not specified.
    r    - Indicate ringing to the calling party. Pass no audio to the calling
           party until the called channel has answered.
    S(x) - Hang up the call after &apos;x&apos; seconds *after* the called party has
           answered the call.
    t    - Allow the called party to transfer the calling party by sending the
           DTMF sequence defined in features.conf.
    T    - Allow the calling party to transfer the called party by sending the
           DTMF sequence defined in features.conf.
    U(x[^arg]) - Execute via Gosub the routine &apos;x&apos; for the *called* channel before connecting
           to the calling channel. Arguments can be specified to the Gosub
           using &apos;^&apos; as a delimiter. The Gosub routine can set the variable
           GOSUB_RESULT to specify the following actions after the Gosub returns.
           * ABORT        Hangup both legs of the call.
           * CONGESTION   Behave as if line congestion was encountered.
           * BUSY         Behave as if a busy signal was encountered.
           * CONTINUE     Hangup the called party and allow the calling party
                          to continue dialplan execution at the next priority.
           * GOTO:&lt;context&gt;^&lt;exten&gt;^&lt;priority&gt; - Transfer the call to the
                          specified priority. Optionally, an extension, or
                          extension and priority can be specified.
           You cannot use any additional action post answer options in conjunction
           with this option. Also, pbx services are not run on the peer (called) channel,
           so you will not be able to set timeouts via the TIMEOUT() function in this routine.
    w    - Allow the called party to enable recording of the call by sending
           the DTMF sequence defined for one-touch recording in features.conf.
    W    - Allow the calling party to enable recording of the call by sending
           the DTMF sequence defined for one-touch recording in features.conf.
    x    - Allow the called party to enable recording of the call by sending
           the DTMF sequence defined for one-touch automixmonitor in features.conf
    X    - Allow the calling party to enable recording of the call by sending
           the DTMF sequence defined for one-touch automixmonitor in features.conf<screen>
