<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<screen>-= Info about application &apos;DISA&apos; =-

[Synopsis]
DISA (Direct Inward System Access)

[Description]
DISA(&lt;numeric passcode&gt;[,&lt;context&gt;[,&lt;cid&gt;[,mailbox[,options]]]]) or
DISA(&lt;filename&gt;[,,,,options])
The DISA, Direct Inward System Access, application allows someone from
outside the telephone switch (PBX) to obtain an &quot;internal&quot; system
dialtone and to place calls from it as if they were placing a call from
within the switch.
DISA plays a dialtone. The user enters their numeric passcode, followed by
the pound sign (#). If the passcode is correct, the user is then given
system dialtone within &lt;context&gt; on which a call may be placed. If the user
enters an invalid extension and extension &quot;i&quot; exists in the specified
context, it will be used.

If you need to present a DISA dialtone without entering a password, simply
set &lt;passcode&gt; to &quot;no-password&quot;.

Be aware that using this may compromise the security of your PBX.

The arguments to this application (in extensions.conf) allow either
specification of a single global passcode (that everyone uses), or
individual passcodes contained in a file.

The file that contains the passcodes (if used) allows a complete
specification of all of the same arguments available on the command
line, with the sole exception of the options. The file may contain blank
lines, or comments starting with &quot;#&quot; or &quot;;&quot;.

&lt;context&gt; specifies the dialplan context in which the user-entered extension
will be matched. If no context is specified, the DISA application defaults
the context to &quot;disa&quot;. Presumably a normal system will have a special
context set up for DISA use with some or a lot of restrictions.

&lt;cid&gt; specifies a new (different) callerid to be used for this call.

&lt;mailbox[@context]&gt; will cause a stutter-dialtone (indication &quot;dialrecall&quot;)
to be used, if the specified mailbox contains any new messages.

The following options are available:
  n - the DISA application will not answer initially.
  p - the extension entered will be considered complete when a &apos;#&apos; is entered.<screen>
