<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="analog" lang="de" revision="$Revision: 1923 $">
  <!--% Copyright (c) 2007 - Stefan Wintermeyer <sw@amooma.de>
% Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
% under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
% or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
% with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover
% Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
% Free Documentation License".
% Asterisk training and consulting is offered at http://www.amooma.de-->

  <title>Analog telephony</title>

  <para>In spite of the increasing adoption of digital and IP transports, the
  classic analog line pair still plays a huge role in communications. Most
  residential land lines in North America are still analog, and many
  businesses rely on analog lines to connect their small PBXes and key
  systems. Analog can have a place in installations that have fax devices,
  which work poorly over IP.</para>

  <para>Two types of device can be attached to a telephone line:<note>
      <para>The name describes what the device is attaching
      <emphasis>to</emphasis>, which can be counter-intuitive.</para>
    </note></para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>FXO – Foreign Exchange Office</para>

      <para>A <emphasis>Foreign eXchange Office</emphasis> (FXO) device is any
      end-user device which attaches to a line and <emphasis>does
      not</emphasis> provide its own line battery voltage. The standard
      telephone we are all familiar with qualifies as an FXO device, but fax
      machines and modems are also FXO devices. A phone is an FXO device
      because it attaches <emphasis>to</emphasis> a Foreign Exchange Office,
      also called a telephone exchange.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>FXS – Foreign Exchange Station</para>

      <para>A <emphasis>Foreign eXchange Station</emphasis> (FXS) is any
      device which provides line battery voltage. This almost always means a
      dial tone and ringing voltage also. You need an FXS device if you need
      to provide service to analog phones, fax machines, and modems. The
      telephone outlet on the wall is a typical FXS "device".</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section>
    <title>Connecting analog devices</title>

    <para>FXS devices provide significant voltage; a telephone line in the
    "on-hook" state can have a voltage as high as 52 volts DC, and a ringing
    line can have a voltage between 90 and 110 volts AC! Keep the AC ringing
    voltage in mind when you are working on an exposed, active line pair with
    bare fingers. While the ringing signal is unlikely to do you any harm, the
    bite can make you quite uncomfortable! If you want to avoid this, wear
    gloves.</para>

    <warning>
      If you attach an FXS module on an interface card to a telephone outlet, it can permanently damage your card or even cause the interruption of service from the telephone company! Use caution when connecting your card to the line. Make absolutely sure you are connecting an FXO device to your incoming phone line pair. Some interface cards actually light up the port with a colored LED to indicate whether the port is FXS (usually green) or FXO (usually red). Failing that, you should mark the ports with a label or marker before you install the interface card in the server.
    </warning>

    <para>In the telephony world, polarity is described by the terms "tip" and
    "ring", which correspond to the parts of the plug used by telephone
    operators in the early days of the telephone system.<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Tip</para>

          <para>This is the positive <literal>(+)</literal>, or ground (the
          "tip" of the plug).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ring</para>

          <para>This is the negative <literal>(-)</literal>, or battery (the
          "ring", just behind the tip). Ring voltage against ground can vary
          from -48 VDC to -52 VDC.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>If the polarity between the device and the line is
    reversed, it can cause problems in some cases. For example, if you have an
    older DTMF phone (such as a Western Electric model 2500), you won't be
    able to dial out; reversed polarity has been known to cause noise problems
    also. Even if most newer devices ignore polarity, it is good practice to
    keep polarity consistent throughout your wiring system. This way, you can
    be guaranteed that your phone system will work properly with any standard
    device.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ata">
    <title>ATA (Analog Telephone Adapter)</title>

    <para>The Analog Telephone Adapter allows you to connect an analog
    telephone device to an IP network (either SIP or IAX2, and almost always
    Ethernet). The advantages are the simplicity and low cost when compared
    with FXS modules on analog interface cards (an ATA can be had for as
    little as 50 USD). Also, FXS modules can suffer from noise caused by
    nearby components in the Asterisk server; an ATA does not suffer from this
    problem. A major disadvantage of an ATA is that won't work any better with
    fax.</para>

    <para>An ATA has one Ethernet port and at least one RJ-11/RJ-12 telephone
    port, sometimes two. An ATA can be configured via an attached telephone or
    through a web interface. ATAs may connect directly to a phone, or be
    connected to the building wiring to support multiple extensions sharing a
    single line.</para>

    <para>A SIP ATA is treated just like any other SIP telephone, and you'll
    need to create an entry for it in <filename>sip.conf</filename>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
