<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE dedication PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="vorwort" lang="de" revision="$Revision: 1687 $">
  <!--
% Copyright (c) 2006 - 2009 by 
% Stefan Wintermeyer <stefan.wintermeyer@amooma.de>
% Philipp Kempgen <philipp.kempgen@amooma.de>
% Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
% under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
% or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
% with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover
% Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
% Free Documentation License".
% Asterisk training and consulting is offered at http://www.amooma.de
-->

  <title>Foreword</title>

  <para>Dear Reader,</para>

  <para>This book was made possible by the sales success of the first edition,
  so I want to thank you.</para>

  <para>The last few years have been active ones in the VoIP world. My work
  with Asterisk has brought me not simply to Digium's headquarters in
  Huntsville, Alabama, but also to Toronto (to visit Sangoma), Chicago
  (ClueCon) and Bucharest (Yate). I learned much about Asterisk, but also a
  lot about <ulink url="http://yate.null.ro/">Yate</ulink> and <ulink
  url="http://www.freeswitch.org/">FreeSwitch</ulink>, both interesting
  open-source VoIP alternatives.</para>

  <para>Asterisk has progressed mightily since the first edition. My
  colleague, Philipp Kempgen, helped me tremendously and has left his mark on
  the new edition. This edition is not only more comprehensive, but also
  better organized than the first. We made it our goal to make this book serve
  as a quick and easy introduction to Asterisk for the beginner, while also
  being a complete reference book for the professional. Leafing through this
  new edition I still find areas I wish I could have expanded on further or
  covered more completely. Maybe that's the lot of the author. Certainly
  Asterisk and VoIP are such large subject areas that one could easily fill
  another two or three books as thick as this one with interesting
  content.</para>

  <para>This edition is being released in both the original German and English
  at the same time. There are some differences in the English edition which
  reflect the different technologies in use in North America, particularly as
  it concerns ISDN. You can find the German edition as per usual at <ulink
  url="http://www.das-asterisk-buch.de">www.das-asterisk-buch.de</ulink> and
  the English version at <ulink
  url="http://www.the-asterisk-book.com">www.the-asterisk-book.com</ulink>.</para>

  <para>Once again, I welcome your feedback, praise and criticism. Please send
  it to me at <email>stefan.wintermeyer@amooma.de</email>.</para>

  <para>&mdash; Stefan Wintermeyer</para>

  <para>Dear Reader,</para>

  <para>It has been a special privilege and a wonderful experience to work
  with Stefan on the translation of this book into English. As it happens,
  Stefan speaks English quite well; being the consummate professional that he
  is, he knew that a competent English version would need a dedicated
  translator. To be entrusted with this task has been an honor. I was also
  charged with some of the adaptations and changes for the English edition,
  including for the chapter on ISDN and for the hardware installation
  chapter.</para>

  <para>Translations are never easy endeavors, but like poetry, a technical
  translation is a special kind of beast. I hope that the book you have in
  your hands proves readable and helpful. Like Stefan, I welcome your
  feedback. Please send it to me at <email>sbosch@vodacomm.ca</email>.</para>

  <para>&mdash; Stephen Bosch</para>
</preface>
