<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="case-study" lang="de" revision="$Revision:495 $">
  <!--% Copyright (c) 2006 - 2007 by 
% Stefan Wintermeyer <sw@amooma.de>
% Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
% under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
% or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
% with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover
% Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
% Free Documentation License".-->

  <!--% translated from the German by Stephen Bosch <sbosch@vodacomm.ca>-->

  <!--% Asterisk training and consulting is offered at http://www.amooma.de-->

  <title>Case example: A typical business telephone system</title>

  <section id="grosse-anlage-einleitung">
    <title id="einleitung">Introduction</title>

    <para>Building on what we've learned in <xref
    linkend="kapitel-installation" />, we'll put together a more comprehensive
    system for a fictional business. This will show you how to handle the
    requirements you're likely to be faced with in real installations.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="personen-der-apfelmus-gmbh">
    <title id="die-apfelmus-gmbh">Widgets, Inc.</title>

    <para>Our fictional company is in the widget manufacturing business. We've
    been charged with the task of planning a phone system for the new office,
    which houses the following departments:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Management (2 people)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Reception (3 people)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Domestic sales (6 people)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>International sales (4 people)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Production (50 people)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Shipping (10 people)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>IT (2 people)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Building manager (1 person)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Every employee has his or her own phone.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="apfelmus-rufnummernplan">
    <title id="rufnummernplan">The numbering plan</title>

    <para>The business has 78 employees. Though it's possible to get by with
    two-digit extension numbers, we'll use three; this leaves us some
    breathing room in the event the company expands or we need more extensions
    (for example, for fax machines or for group numbers).</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Number range</emphasis></entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Explanation</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>911</entry>

            <entry>Emergency number</entry>

            <entry>Emergency numbers should be absolutely intuitive. In the
            case of fire or serious injury, no employee should have to think
            twice about what number to dial.<footnote>
                <para>9-1-1 is the universal emergency number for the North
                American Numbering Plan (NANP). If you are configuring systems
                for an international business, you may wish to consider adding
                9-9-9 and 1-1-2 as well, as these are standard emergency
                numbers for the UK and continental Europe,
                respectively.</para>
              </footnote></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>150 - 159</entry>

            <entry>Building manager</entry>

            <entry>The building manager is responsible for all building
            operations.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>160 - 169</entry>

            <entry>IT</entry>

            <entry>The IT department is responsible for computer and network
            operations.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>200 - 229</entry>

            <entry>Management</entry>

            <entry>The executive offices have 2XX extensions.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>230 - 269</entry>

            <entry>Reception</entry>

            <entry>As reception will be fielding calls mostly to management,
            they have numbers in the range 230-269. Numbers from 270-299 are
            kept in reserve.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>300 - 349</entry>

            <entry>Domestic Sales</entry>

            <entry>Sales gets the entire 3XX number block, to ensure adequate
            reserve in case of expansion. The first 50 numbers are allocated
            to Domestic Sales.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>350 - 399</entry>

            <entry>International Sales</entry>

            <entry>The second 50 numbers are allocated to International
            Sales.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>400 - 449</entry>

            <entry>Shipping</entry>

            <entry>The first half of the 4XX number block is allocated to
            Shipping.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>500 - 599</entry>

            <entry>Production</entry>

            <entry>Production is the largest department and gets the entire
            5XX block.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>800 - 899</entry>

            <entry>Internal services</entry>

            <entry>Special services and non-standard extensions,
            <emphasis>e.g.</emphasis>, voicemail or teleconferencing.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>

  <section id="apfelmus-infrastruktur">
    <title>Choice of infrastructure</title>

    <para>The new building is getting a modern structured cabling system, so
    it makes sense to equip each workstation with a SIP phone. This saves us
    the grief and extra expense of running telephone wiring in parallel to the
    network wiring. Fax machines and cordless telephones can be connected to
    the system using analog telephone adapter (ATA) devices.<warning>
        <para>Faxing in Asterisk is nevertheless problematic. VoIP
        connections, depending on how they are compressed, can have less
        bandwidth available than a fax connection requires. This can result in
        fax transmissions being only partially received, or worse, failing
        completely. If you are only using VoIP internally, you must ensure
        that the codecs you choose can adequately support fax. The better
        option is to use an analog telephony card to provide internal analog
        extensions purely for fax use, or, ideally, build fax server
        functionality into Asterisk (see <xref
        linkend="kapitel-fax" />).</para>
      </warning>We install the Asterisk server in a climate-controlled server
    room with controlled access. Only authorized personnel are to have access
    to the server.<footnote>
        <para>In the past it was common for PBX and key system manufacturers
        to build secret backdoors into their systems, mainly for the purpose
        of providing timely support in the event of an outage. It was
        inevitable that clever but unscrupulous parties would figure out a way
        to exploit these backdoors to make free long distance and
        international calls, mostly at the expense of public institutions too
        large to have a clear picture of how their systems were configured. In
        today's world, the security of your systems, be they Asterisk or
        anything else, should always be a paramount concern.</para>
      </footnote></para>

    <section id="apfelmus-netzwerk">
      <title>Network</title>

      <para>The network is such a significant aspect of Asterisk's
      functionality that it demands a more thorough discussion.</para>

      <para>Telephony is a synchronous medium, which means that the receiver
      must accept the sender's transmission the instant it is sent. Human
      beings can tolerate a delay (also known as <quote>latency</quote>) of up
      to 300 ms (milliseconds), though the delay can be perceptible when over
      100 ms and distracting when over 200 ms. Most people find anything over
      500 ms unacceptable. This is the principal challenge that IP telephony
      must address: in IP telephony, we are attempting to carry a synchronous
      data stream over an asynchronous medium. The TCP/IP protocol, developed
      with funding from the US Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency
      (DARPA), was designed to maximize stability and robustness, but it
      achieves this at the expense of the kind of real-time performance we
      would expect of a telephone connection.</para>

      <para>When an e-mail suffers an occasional pause in transmission, it is
      materially unaffected. A voice conversation, by contrast, is highly
      time-dependent. If someone says <quote>Hi</quote> to us, we expect it to
      be followed by something relevant and intelligble immediately (such as
      <quote>there!</quote> for example), because that is the way people speak
      to each other in person. That we can even carry voice traffic on an IP
      connection is owing to the high performance of modern network hardware.
      The high bandwidth of modern networks coupled with the relatively small
      bandwidth required by a single telephone-grade voice conversation means
      that voice traffic can be carried in a pseudo-real-time fashion.</para>

      <para>Nevertheless, network conditions vary, both by site and in time. A
      big network with many endpoints will carry a lot of traffic; networks
      also tend to be busier during normal business hours (say from 8 a.m. to
      6 p.m.) while employees send and receive e-mail, surf the web, download
      programs and documents, etc. This happens to be the time they make most
      of their telephone calls, and things can reach a critical point very
      quickly. If the available bandwidth drops below the minimum needed, we
      will start to see packet delay or loss. When this happens, the effect on
      voice conversations is drastic and immediate, resulting in dropouts,
      clipped words, clicks, pops and other strange noises. Anybody who has
      any experience with wireless telephone service knows how distracting
      this can be.</para>

      <para>To deal with these eventualities, commercial-grade routers and
      most managed switches support some kind of traffic
      classification.</para>

      <para><footnote>
          <para>TOS - Type Of Service</para>
        </footnote></para>

      <para>By setting a TOS flag in voice packets, we can prioritize traffic
      passing through the router or switch. This feature is useful for
      managing traffic inside our network and across the network boundary, but
      it has no impact once the packets are on the Internet service provider's
      (ISP) network or on the public Internet. Only once the ISP guarantees
      low latency and bandwidth for real-time traffic<footnote>
          <para>QOS - Quality Of Service</para>
        </footnote>can we have an assurance of call quality. If you will be
      supporting a multi-branch operation and plan to connect them with VoIP,
      you should consider this requirement carefully and discuss it with your
      ISP.</para>

      <para>The Asterisk system for Widgets, Inc. has at least 78 physical
      stations. In the worst case, we will have 39 simultaneous conversations
      (this happens if all the employees call each other). Depending on the
      codec used, we can expect a maximum bandwidth of 6,500 kbps<footnote>
          <para>kbps = kilobits per second</para>
        </footnote>, which should be no problem for a typical 100
      Mbps<footnote>
          <para>Mbps = Megabits per second, also 1.024 kbps</para>
        </footnote>LAN on structured, twisted-pair cable. All the same, this
      network will be carrying other traffic, and a couple of big file
      transfers can be enough to hit performance limits.</para>

      <para>How do we get the 6,500 kbps value? The standard G.711 compression
      standard includes two companding algorithms, u-law (used in North
      American and Japan) and a-law (used in Europe).<footnote>
          <para>These two algorithms are used for carrying voice traffic in
          ISDN channels (such as those used in T1 and T3 connections; see
          <xref linkend="kapitel-ISDN" />)</para>
        </footnote>These provide excellent sound quality, but need at least 64
      kbps bandwidth. A single connection consists of an incoming and outgoing
      channel, each at 64 kbps; 39 connections add up as follows: 2 x 39 x 64
      kbps = 4,992 kbps. In addition to the channel bandwidth required, there
      will also be TCP/IP network overhead, so that each channel will use
      about 80 kbps in total. Now our total is 6,280 kbps; round up, and we
      have 6,500 kbps. While this is only a worst-case scenario, when it comes
      to voice systems, it is better to be safe than sorry!<footnote>
          <para>The website <ulink
          url="http://www.asteriskguru.com/tools/bandwidth_calculator.php">http://www.asteriskguru.com/tools/bandwidth_calculator.php</ulink>
          has an Asterisk bandwidth calculator with bandwidth values for
          various codecs that can help you the planning process.</para>
        </footnote><tip>
          <para>If you have doubts over whether you have sufficient bandwidth
          available to support all your extensions, consider starting with a
          lossier codec such as GSM. At betwen 13 and 15 kbps per channel, it
          needs only a fifth of the bandwidth of u-law and delivers adequate
          sound quality for most applications. Once you've verified the
          stability of your system, you can try switching groups of extensions
          over to u-law and wait to see if you have network problems as a
          result. Just remember highly compressive codecs like GSM are more
          processor-intensive, so you need to ensure you have adequate CPU
          resources available on your Asterisk server.</para>
        </tip></para>
    </section>

    <section id="apfelmus-server-hardware">
      <title>Server hardware</title>

      <para>The choice of server hardware for the Asterisk server is subject
      to many of the same considerations. The need for synchronous, real-time
      data transfer requires timely handling of the necessary processes in
      Asterisk. Most of the computing effort comes in the coding and decoding
      of digital sound streams; this effort is even greater if you have
      equipment that uses different codecs and Asterisk has to
      transcode<footnote>
          <para>Transcoding is the process by which an audio stream in one
          codec is translated into another codec. For example, a connection
          between a device supporting only GSM and one supporting only G.711
          will have to be transcoded; this is normally done by
          Asterisk.</para>
        </footnote> between them. The tremendous variety and quantity of
      hardware available means there is no hard and fast rule for calculating
      processor requirements. As a guide, however, we can start with this
      table:</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>CPU</entry>

              <entry>Number of simultaneous connections</entry>

              <entry>Number of endpoints</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>1,0 GHz</entry>

              <entry>15</entry>

              <entry>40</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>1,5 GHz</entry>

              <entry>40</entry>

              <entry>100</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>2,0 GHz</entry>

              <entry>80</entry>

              <entry>200</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>By <quote>CPU</quote> we mean a typical CPU from an off-the-shelf
      PC (<emphasis>e.g.</emphasis> <trademark>Intel</trademark> or
      <trademark>AMD</trademark>). We've calculated the number of simultaneous
      connections based on the reasonable assumption that not all the phones
      will be active at one time, but rather between one-third and one-half.
      It should be noted that this is just a coarse estimate with a
      considerable margin of safety; If there is little transcoding,
      conferencing or echo cancellation required, the number of simultaneous
      connections supported would be higher. That said, the exact limits for
      any given installation can only be reliably determined through direct
      testing and experimentation.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>The Linux program <command>top</command> provides a simple tool
        for monitoring processor loads on a running server, but only at the
        current point in time. Processor and process loads are inherently
        dynamic and change dramatically from one moment to the next, so point
        measurements have limited usefulness. You can try monitoring the
        performance of your Asterisk servers using monitoring tools like
        Nagios <ulink
        url="http://www.nagios.org">(http://www.nagios.org</ulink>). If you
        prefer to use native Linux tools, you can do simple monitoring with a
        <command>cron</command> job (see <command>man crontab</command>)
        running a <command>bash</command> script with this
        content:<programlisting>w | head -n 1 &gt;&gt; /var/log/serverloads</programlisting></para>

        <para>By running this <command>cron</command> job every minute, you
        will build up a set of data points over time which you can use to
        evaluate server performance.<footnote>
            <para>This cron job would indeed be a very simple analysis tool.
            If you are comfortable with shell scripting, you can write more
            comprehensive scripts which can give you more detailed information
            by using output from tools like <command>top</command> and
            <command>uptime</command>, processing it, and dumping the
            processed output into a comma-delimited text file which you can
            graph in a spreadsheet program.</para>
          </footnote></para>
      </tip>

      <para>Widgets, Inc. has 78 employees and an estimate of 40 simultaneous
      connections is reasonable, so a computer with a reasonably current
      CPU<footnote>
          <para>For example, Pentium 4, AMD Athlon</para>
        </footnote></para>

      <para>at a clock speed of 1.5 GHz should suffice. In general, the newer
      the CPU and system, the better the performance; processor clock speed is
      no longer an accurate measure of CPU performance, particularly as
      applied to the newer dual-core processors, and your server will likely
      be able to handle more calls with a newer processor at the same clock
      speed. Dual processor machines will improve performance
      correspondingly.</para>

      <para>For the voice mailboxes, we will need about 0.1 MB (megabytes) of
      disk space per minute of message time.<footnote>
          <para>This is for wav49 or GSM format message files. If you decide
          to use uncompressed WAV format files, you will use many times the
          space. As disk space is cheap, this is not normally an issue, and
          more installations are using uncompressed WAV because of the higher
          sound quality. Be mindful, though, that more disk space used means
          more storage required for backup.</para>
        </footnote>If we allot 30 minutes of message storage to each user, we
      can expect to use a total of about 2 GB (gigabytes) of disk space.
      Because voice message data is valuable business data and can even be
      critical, the storage should be redundant and backed-up regularly. A
      RAID 1 array<footnote>
          <para>Note that software RAID burdens the CPU significantly. A
          professional installation should use hardware RAID.</para>
        </footnote>(two disks or disk sets in a mirror configuration) will
      provide the necessary redundancy.</para>

      <para>Memory requirements for Asterisk are not onerous, and 512 MB RAM
      would be adequate. With 1 GB RAM, Asterisk can handle very large
      business units. Any additional steps taken to enhance the reliability
      and performance of the server, such as the installation of redundant
      network adapters, commercial-grade telephone interface cards, and
      uninterruptible power supplies will go a long way to increasing user and
      decision-maker confidence in the system. If your background is in IT
      services, you are facing a whole new level of user expectations. Users
      will usually tolerate a brief e-mail outage; the phones, however,
      absolutely must work <emphasis>always</emphasis>. Readers with a
      background in circuit-switched telephony will know exactly what we are
      talking about.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="apfelmus-grundkonfiguration">
    <title>Base configuration</title>

    <para>We'll configure Asterisk so that all the employees can call each
    other and have their own mailbox. Once that's done, the system can be
    extended with additional functions and modules.</para>

    <section id="apfelmus-sip.conf">
      <title>sip.conf for up to 100 users</title>

      <para>Configuring <filename>/etc/asterisk/sip.conf</filename> for 100
      users is no different than configuring for 2 users; there are no
      shortcuts here. Each SIP extension must be configured individually. What
      follows is an abridged version of the <filename>sip.conf</filename> for
      Widgets, Inc. Lines beginning with the <code>;</code> are treated as
      comments and ignored by Asterisk. The file is composed in the same way
      as in our simple example in chapter 1. In general we've avoided
      assigning numbers to individual users that end in 0, because we want to
      reserve those numbers for group phone numbers. The building manager is
      an exception, since we don't anticipate any need for a group phone
      number there.</para>

      <programlisting>[general]
port = 5060
bindaddr = 0.0.0.0
context = sonstige

; Hausmeister
;
[150]  ; normal office phone
context=building-mgr
secret=1234
callerid="Building Manager" &lt;150&gt;
type=friend
host=dynamic

[151]  ; cordless phone
context=building-mgr
secret=1234
callerid="Building Manager" &lt;150&gt;
type=friend
host=dynamic

; Internal IT department
;
[161]  ; Tech 1
context=it
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[162]  ; Tech 2
context=it
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[165]  ; Cordless phone
context=it
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

; Executive offices
;
[201]  ; Manager 1
context=management
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[202]  ; Manager 2
context=management
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

; Reception
;
[231]  ; Assistant 1
context=sekretariat
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[232]  ; Assistant 2
context=reception
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[233]  ; Assistant 3
context=reception
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

; Domestic Sales
;
[301]  ; Account Agent 1
context=domestic-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[302]  ; Account Agent 2
context=domestic-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[303]  ; Account Agent 3
context=domestic-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[304]  ; Account Agent 4
context=domestic-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[305]  ; Account Agent 5
context=domestic-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[306]  ; Account Agent 6
context=domestic-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

; International Sales
;
[351]  ; Account Agent 1
context=international-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[352]  ; Account Agent 2
context=international-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[353]  ; Account Agent 3
context=international-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

[354]  ; Account Agent 4
context=international-sales
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

; Shipping
;
[401]  ; Shipping Agent 1
context=shipping
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

; The remaining 9 entries for Shipping are omitted here for the sake of brevity.

; Production
;
[501]  ; Assembly line 1
context=production
secret=1234
type=friend
host=dynamic

; die weiteren 49 Eintraege fuer die 
; Produktion sind hier ausgelassen.</programlisting>

      <para>Wer die sip.conf komfortabler mit Templates gestalten will, findet
      im <xref linkend="anhang-conf-templates" /> weitere Informationen
      dazu.</para>

      <section id="apfelmus-callerid">
        <title>CallerID</title>

        <para>In der <filename>sip.conf</filename> kommt zweimal die Variable
        <code>callerid</code> vor. Mit dieser Variable wird festgelegt, was
        beim Angerufenen auf dem Display angezeigt wird. Im konkreten
        Beispiel:<programlisting>callerid = "Hausmeister" &lt;150&gt;</programlisting>Dies
        sagt aus, dass sich beide Telefone (150 und 151) mit der Caller-ID 150
        und dem Text ''Hausmeister'' zu erkennen geben. Dadurch ist
        sichergestellt, dass Rückrufe immer nur auf die 150 gehen.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="apfelmus-dialplan">
      <title>Der Wählplan (Dialplan)</title>

      <para>Im ersten Kapitel haben wir schon einen einfachen Dialplan für
      zwei Telefone erstellt. Diesmal haben wir jedoch deutlich mehr
      Teilnehmer und obwohl es im Grunde lediglich Fleißarbeit bedeutet, ist
      die Pflege einer Konfiguration mit einigen Hundert Teilnehmern
      zeitaufwändig. Weiterhin fördert eine schlechte Übersichtlichkeit das
      Einschleichen von Fehlern. Aus diesen Gründen beschäftigen wir uns am
      Anfang dieses Abschnitts mit ein paar Asterisk-Funktionen, die uns das
      Leben einfacher und die <filename>extensions.conf</filename>
      übersichtlicher machen.</para>

      <section id="apfelmus-pattern-matching">
        <title>Platzhalter - Pattern Matching</title>

        <para>Asterisk bietet die Möglichkeit mit Platzhaltern<footnote>
            <para>Unix- und Linux-Fans werden das Konzept des ''Pattern
            Matching'' von den ''regulären Ausdrücken'' in Programmen wie
            <command>grep</command> und <command>sed</command> kennen.</para>
          </footnote> zu arbeiten. Durch sinnvolles Gruppieren von
        Nummernblöcken und Zuordnungen können mit Platzhaltern ganze
        Nummernbereiche mit einzelnen Konfigurationszeilen verwaltet werden.
        Im Prinzip enthält eine Konfigurationszeile einen variablen
        Nummernbereich, der mit Hilfe von ''Pattern Matching'' die definierte
        Regel auf eine Vielzahl von Nummern anwendet. So kann man anstatt der
        folgenden 10 Zeilen: <programlisting>exten =&gt; 2000,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)
exten =&gt; 2001,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)
exten =&gt; 2002,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20) 
exten =&gt; 2003,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)
exten =&gt; 2004,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)
exten =&gt; 2005,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)
exten =&gt; 2006,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)
exten =&gt; 2007,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)
exten =&gt; 2008,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)
exten =&gt; 2009,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)</programlisting>auch nur eine Zeile
        schreiben:</para>

        <programlisting>exten =&gt; _200X,1,Dial(SIP/2000,20)</programlisting>

        <para>Das <code>X</code> steht dann für alle Zahlen von 0 bis
        9.<footnote>
            <para>Das Beispiel macht natürlich wenig Sinn. Warum sollte der
            Anrufer die 2009 wählen, um zur 2000 verbunden zu werden? Zur
            Lösung dieses Problems kommen wir gleich.</para>
          </footnote> Wichtig dabei ist, dass der Suchbegriff (das Pattern)
        mit einem <code>_</code> (Underscore) anfängt, sonst würde Asterisk
        nur auf <code>200X</code> (also eine 200 und den Buchstaben X)
        reagieren, da ja Nebenstellen nicht nur aus Ziffern bestehen
        können/müssen. Das Definieren von Platzhaltern mit Pattern
        Matching<footnote>
            <para>Es gibt keinen wirklich passenden deutschen Begriff zum
            Fachbegriff ''Pattern Matching''. Eine mögliche Übersetzung könnte
            ''Musterabgleich'' oder ''Mustervergleich'' lauten.</para>
          </footnote> beinhaltet, dass man bestimmte Zeichenketten oder
        Zahlenfolgen durch entsprechend vordefinierte Platzhalter
        ersetzt.</para>

        <para>In Asterisk kann man folgende Patterns benutzen:</para>

        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Beschreibung</emphasis></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>X</code></entry>

                <entry>Alle Zahlen von 0 bis 9</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>Z</code></entry>

                <entry>Alle Zahlen von 1 bis 9</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>N</code></entry>

                <entry>Alle Zahlen von 2 bis 9<footnote>
                    <para>Der Grund für das Pattern <code>N</code> liegt in
                    der Rufnummernplanung von Amerika. Dort beginnt die
                    Vorwahl nicht wie in Deutschland mit einer 0, sondern mit
                    einer 1. Beispiel: 1-555-12345678</para>
                  </footnote></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>[nm]</code></entry>

                <entry>Die Zahlen n und m</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>[n-m]</code></entry>

                <entry>Alle Zahlen von n bis m</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><code>.</code></entry>

                <entry>Eine oder mehrere beliebige Zahlen und
                Buchstaben</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

        <warning>
          <para>Ein Pattern muss immer mit einem <code>_</code> (Underscore)
          anfangen!</para>

          <para>Für Asterisk ist sowohl ein <code>2XXX</code> als auch ein
          <code>_2XXX</code> als Wert sinnvoll, wird jedoch vollkommen
          unterschiedlich ausgewertet.</para>
        </warning>

        <section id="apfelmus-patternbeispiele">
          <title>Beispiele für Patterns</title>

          <para>Die folgenden Varianten dienen als Beispiele für die
          Möglichkeiten:</para>

          <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern</emphasis></entry>

                  <entry><emphasis role="bold">Beschreibung</emphasis></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>_XXX</entry>

                  <entry>Alle 3-stelligen Zahlen. Wobei auch <code>007</code>
                  eine 3-stellige Zahl ist.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>_XXX[13579]</entry>

                  <entry>Alle 4-stelligen Zahlen, die ungerade sind.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>_[1-5]X</entry>

                  <entry>Alle 2-stelligen Zahlen von 10 bis 59.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>_0.</entry>

                  <entry>Eine beliebige Zeichenkette, die mit einer 0
                  anfängt.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>_.</entry>

                  <entry>Alles! Sollte mit entsprechender Vorsicht benutzt
                  werden, da es immer mit der höchsten Priorität gematcht
                  wird.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>

          <para>Detailierte Informationen zum Thema Pattern Matching finden
          Sie in <xref linkend="regular-expression" />.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section id="apfelmus-exten-var">
        <title>Die Variable ${EXTEN}</title>

        <para>Obwohl wir eigentlich erst später über Variablen sprechen,
        möchte ich eine sehr einfache und intuitiv zu benutzende Variable
        schon hier vorstellen. Es handelt sich um <code>${EXTEN}</code>. In
        dieser Variable ist die gewählte Nummer gespeichert. Ich kann also in
        der <filename>extensions.conf</filename> anstatt:<programlisting>exten =&gt; 2000,1,Dial(SIP/2000)</programlisting>auch
        einfach<programlisting>exten =&gt; 2000,1,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN})</programlisting>schreiben.
        Bei einer Zeile ist das natürlich noch wenig sinnvoll, aber wenn man
        diese Funktionalität mit Pattern Matching kombiniert, dann kann man
        sehr viel Zeit und Aufwand sparen und bekommt zusätzlich auch noch
        eine viel übersichtlichere Konfiguration.</para>

        <para>Um somit alle SIP-Telefone mit den Durchwahlen 2000 bis 2999 in
        der <filename>extensions.conf</filename> anwählbar zu machen, reicht
        folgende Zeile:<programlisting>exten =&gt; _2XXX,1,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN})</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section id="apfelmus-include">
        <title>Include</title>

        <para>Innerhalb der <filename>extensions.conf</filename> können
        Bereiche mit einem <code>include =&gt; Contextname</code> eingefügt
        werden. So kann man eine einmal erstellte Definition in mehreren
        Contexten wiederverwenden. Beispiel:<programlisting>[telefone-im-ersten-stock]
include =&gt; 2000er
include =&gt; anrufbeantworter

[telefone-im-zweiten-stock]
include =&gt; 2000er
include =&gt; anrufbeantworter

[telefone-im-dritten-stock]
include =&gt; 2000er

[2000er]
exten =&gt; _2XXX,1,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN})

[anrufbeantworter]
exten =&gt; 3000,1,VoicemailMain(${CALLERID(num)})</programlisting>Der Vorteil
        dieses Weges ist, dass wenn man z.B. die Rufnummer des
        Anrufbeantworters ändern will, es reicht, dieses genau in einem
        Bereich zu machen.</para>

        <tip>
          <para>Die Funktion <code>${CALLERID(num)}</code> übergibt die Nummer
          des Anrufenden. So kann die Applikation <code>VoiceMailMain()</code>
          mit dieser Variable aufgerufen werden und fragt dann nicht mehr nach
          der Mailbox, sondern nur noch nach dem Passwort der entsprechenden
          Mailbox.</para>
        </tip>

        <warning>
          <para>Wer intensiv mit Includes arbeitet, sollte <xref
          linkend="includes-im-dialplan" /> lesen.</para>
        </warning>
      </section>

      <section id="apfelmus-extensions.conf">
        <title>Die extensions.conf für die Apfelmus GmbH</title>

        <para>Der von uns entwickelte Rufnummernplan<footnote>
            <para>Mit Ausnahme der Notrufnummern, die wir später behandeln, da
            wir jetzt noch keine Verbindung zur Außenwelt eingerichtet
            haben.</para>
          </footnote> lässt sich nun wie folgt in eine übersichtliche
        <filename>extensions.conf</filename> übertragen:<programlisting>[others]

[hausmeister]
include =&gt; interne-gespraeche
include =&gt; voicemailsystem-komfort

[it]
include =&gt; interne-gespraeche
include =&gt; voicemailsystem-komfort
;
; Aus Debugging Gruenden ist es fuer
; die IT Abteilung teilweise nuetzlich
; auf alle Voicemailboxen zugreifen 
; zu koennen.
;
include =&gt; voicemailsystem-normal

[geschaeftsfuehrer]
include =&gt; interne-gespraeche
include =&gt; voicemailsystem-komfort

[reception]
include =&gt; interne-gespraeche
include =&gt; voicemailsystem-komfort

[domestic-sales]
include =&gt; interne-gespraeche
include =&gt; voicemailsystem-komfort

[international-sales]
include =&gt; interne-gespraeche
include =&gt; voicemailsystem-komfort

[versand]
include =&gt; interne-gespraeche
include =&gt; voicemailsystem-komfort

[production]
include =&gt; interne-gespraeche
include =&gt; voicemailsystem-komfort

[interne-gespraeche]
exten =&gt; _[1-5]XX,1,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN},60)
exten =&gt; _[1-5]XX,2,VoiceMail(${EXTEN},u)

[voicemailsystem-komfort]
;
; Der User muss nicht die Nummer der 
; Voicemailbox eingeben.
;
exten =&gt; 800,1,VoicemailMain(${CALLERID(num)})

[voicemailsystem-normal]
exten =&gt; 801,1,VoicemailMain()</programlisting>Der Context
        <code>[interne-gespraeche]</code> definiert, dass alle Anrufe an die
        Nummern 100 bis 599 mit dem Programm <application>Dial()</application>
        auch mit dieser Nebenstelle verbunden werden. Wer die 800 anruft,
        bekommt die Voicemailbox für sein eigenes Telefon. Nur die
        IT-Abteilung kann die 801 anrufen und wird dann vom System erst nach
        der gewünschten Nebenstelle (Extension) gefragt. Da die IT-Abteilung
        auch den internen Support der Telefonanlage zur Verfügung stellt,
        benötigt sie diese Funktion zur Störungsermittlung (Debugging).</para>

        <section id="schwarze-loecher-im-dialplan">
          <title>Schwarze Löcher im Rufnummernplan</title>

          <para>Genau genommen müsste dieser Dialplan noch etwas komplexer
          sein, da es ja laut Rufnummernplan Bereiche gibt (z.B. 270 bis 299),
          die gar nicht mit Telefonen belegt sind. Da wir dies nicht beachten,
          kann es zu Missverständnissen kommen. Ein Anrufer kann eine nicht
          vergebene Rufnummer anrufen und dort auf dem Anrufbeantworter eine
          Nachricht hinterlassen. Diese Nachricht würde aber nie abgehört
          werden. Um dies zu vermeiden, müsste man korrekterweise den Context
          <code>[interne-gespraeche]</code> wie folgt
          gestalten:<programlisting>[interne-gespraeche]
exten =&gt; _1[5-6]X,1,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN},60)
exten =&gt; _1[5-6]X,2,VoiceMail(${EXTEN},u)

exten =&gt; _2[0-6]X,1,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN},60)
exten =&gt; _2[0-6]X,2,VoiceMail(${EXTEN},u)

exten =&gt; _[358]XX,1,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN},60)
exten =&gt; _[358]XX,2,VoiceMail(${EXTEN},u)

exten =&gt; _4[0-4]XX,1,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN},60)
exten =&gt; _4[0-4]XX,2,VoiceMail(${EXTEN},u)
</programlisting>Wir verzichten bei der Apfelmus GmbH der Einfachheit halber
          auf diese ausführlichere Variante und benutzen nur den folgenden
          Context:<programlisting>[interne-gespraeche]
exten =&gt; _[1-5]XX,1,Dial(SIP/${EXTEN},60)
exten =&gt; _[1-5]XX,2,VoiceMail(${EXTEN},u)
</programlisting></para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section id="apfelmus-voicemail.conf">
        <title>voicemail.conf</title>

        <para>Die <filename>voicemail.conf</filename> bleibt wie im ersten
        Kapitel beschrieben. Es werden einfach nur ein paar mehr Einträge
        eingefügt:</para>

        <programlisting>[general]
format = gsm
serveremail = voicemail@apfelmus-gmbh.de
maxmessage = 600

[local]
150 =&gt; 999999,Hans Hausmeister,hausmeister@apfelmus-gmbh.de
200 =&gt; 999999,Ernst Wichtig,ernst.wichtig@apfelmus-gmbh.de
201 =&gt; 999999,Hans Toll,hans.toll@apfelmus-gmbh.de

; Ich verzichte hier darauf, die restlichen Eintraege aufzulisten, sie sind analog zu den aufgefuehrten Zeilen</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="apfelmus-weiter">
    <title>Wie geht es weiter?</title>

    <para>Die hier besprochene Konfiguration der Apfelmus GmbH dient als
    Planungsbeispiel für alle Anlagen dieser Größenordnung. Einige Beispiele
    in diesem Buch können Sie mit dieser Konfiguration durchspielen.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="apfelmus-faq">
    <title>FAQ</title>

    <para></para>

    <qandaset>
      <qandadiv>
        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>Welche Kosten kommen auf die Apfelmus GmbH zu?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>Das hängt ganz von den Entscheidern in dieser Firma ab.
            Folgende Faktoren spielen dabei eine Rolle:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Soll der Asterisk-Server ausfallsicher sein? Reicht ein
                Cold-Standby oder soll es ein Hot-Standby sein?</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Welche Server-Hardware wird gekauft? Für eine solche
                Telefonanlage reicht ein relativ normaler Rechner. Es muss
                also nicht das allerneueste und damit oft auch teuerste System
                gekauft werden.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Welche Telefone werden eingesetzt? Hierbei kann man von
                30 bis weit über 300 Euro pro Telefon ausgeben.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>

        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>Lohnt sich Asterisk für die Apfelmus GmbH oder handelt es
            sich vielmehr um eine Arbeitsbeschaffungsmaßnahme für die
            IT-Abteilung?</para>
          </question>

          <answer>
            <para>Das hängt stark von den Angeboten der klassischen
            Telefonanlagenherstellern und von den Bedürfnissen der Apfelmus
            GmbH ab. Oft bieten klassische Telefonanlagenhersteller extreme
            Sonderrabatte, wenn sie erfahren, dass als Alternative das
            kostenlose Asterisk in Erwägung gezogen wird. Allerdings ist man
            dann meistens in einem starren Vertrag und kann die nächsten 5
            Jahre nur bei diesem Hersteller einkaufen.</para>

            <para>Einer der großen Vorteile von Asterisk ist die Wahl des
            Supports und des Consultings. Man kann entweder alles selber
            machen oder einen externen Consultant einkaufen. Sollte dieser
            nicht den Ansprüchen genügen, kann man ihn gegen einen anderen
            austauschen (das ist so mit einer klassischen Telefonanlage wegen
            der Vertragsbindung nicht möglich).</para>

            <para>Ob sich Asterisk betriebswirtschaftlich lohnt, muss jeder
            für seinen individuellen Fall ausrechnen. Die Erfahrung zeigt,
            dass dies in den meisten Fällen der Fall ist. Berücksichtigt man
            noch die Möglichkeiten einer Erweiterung mit neuen Funktionen
            durch ein einfaches Softwareupdate, dann entwickeln sich die
            mittel- bis langfristigen Unterhalts- und Investitionskosten
            äußerst günstig.</para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>
      </qandadiv>
    </qandaset>
  </section>
</chapter>